Welcome back to a push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. So, we already know this.
Settlers are moving west because of
gold, opportunity, farming, blah blah
blah. Now, we are going to talk about
the effects of this. So, we already
talked about the transcontinental
railroad. What we didn't talk about was
that the people building this railroad
were mostly Chinese and Irish
immigrants. And understand that this was
no easy job. A very dangerous explosive
called nitroglycerin was constantly used
to blow out tunnels, and it would make
it very dangerous to work on these
railroads. Another thing to know is this
animal right here. In 1860, there were
an estimated 30 million bison in the
United States. By 1884, there were less
than a [music] thousand. So, how the
heck did this happen? Well, railroads
split the herds. Companies hired hunters
to kill them for hides. And the US
military encouraged killing them to
force native tribes off the plains. But
that isn't even talking about the worst
part. Let's look at our standard US map.
West? Well, what is west? Gold,
obviously, right? No, I mean the people
actually originally inhabiting the land.
Yeah, Native Americans still exist and
they are still trying to live freely in
the west. But by this point, Americans
had so many incentives to move west that
they didn't just ignore native peoples.
They actively despised them simply for
living on the land. Treaties that once
promised native sovereignty were
completely violated. America would
switch to a reservation policy and force
native tribes to live on specific
reservation lands. And this did not sue
many native cultures. So did the natives
fight back? Of course they did. It
started with Sand Creek, which was the
first major show of federal betrayal.
The Red River War ended native
resistance in Texas and Oklahoma. The
Nez Perse War ended organized resistance
in the Northwest. The Apache Wars
dragged on for decades, but ended when
the Donimo surrendered in 1886. Now,
there were native victories, too, like
the Sue Wars and the Battle of Little
Bigghorn, but those winds were
temporary. Everything all came crashing
down with the Daw Act in 1887. This
divided native land into private plots,
giving the quote surplus to white
settlers. This led to the loss of over
90 million acres of native land. And
around the same time, a spiritual
movement called the ghost dance spread
among tribes. It symbolized hope for a
world without white domination. [music]
And of course, the US white dominated
military saw it as a threat. And it all
culminated in the Wounded Knee Massacre.
This would kill 300 natives and end the
so-called Indian Wars across America.
The Indians being the obvious losers. If
you can't tell, America are not the good
guys here. They took land they promised
not to take and killed thousands in the
process.
>> [music]
>> In fact, if you live in any of these
states, you are living on technical
stolen land as we speak. It's
unfortunately one of the darkest parts
of American history. With that, here are
your AP style questions.
On the screen now are your answers.
I will see you in the next one.